This video describes how to prepare the child and mother, or care, before performing the fund-red
reflex tests in both newborns and older children.
The child should be held securely, yet comfortably,
either on the lap over a shoulder, or if baby lying on their back.
It is important for them to feel safe.
Young babies can be restless and may need to be swaddled.
Examining shortly after a feed can help as they will be relaxed and a little sleepy.
All our children may settle by playing with a toy for a short while.
Speak with a friendly tone and try to get down to their eyes level.
Explain what you are going to do and gain concept before you start.
First, ask the mother or care if they have not any wrong with their
child's eye or vision
and how long they have not the problem.
Next, look at the child's face and eyes.
Ask yourself some questions.
Does the child seem to have pain in one or both eyes?
Are the eyes open
or are they keeping them tightly shut?
Is there watering or discharge from the eyes?
Are the eyes the same size?
Are the eyelids swollen?
Now, consider how the child is seeing.
Move your face slowly from side to side, watching the eyes.
Make some silent smile.
Does the child follow the movement of your face?
Or respond to your silent smile?
Again ask yourself some questions.
Do both eyes move freely and together?
Are the eyes straight, or is one eye turning inwards or outwards?
Do the eyes wobble?
You can also use the flashlights on the arclights and the pictures of the
bed to gain attention
and assess the quality of vision.
Move the target side to side up and down.
Look to see if the child is fixing and following the targets.
When they reach and point accurately at the
target, often only one eye cannot see well.
You or mother can cover one eye, then the other.
Move the target and compare how the child behaves to when using both eyes,
then one at a time.
If the child does not like one eye being covered, it suggests the uncovered
eye does not see
so well.
If you think you can see something wrong with the external eye, look more
closely using the
loop end of the atlight.
Switch the lights on and move up close to around 6 cm.
You may need to use your finger to gently open the eyelids.
Ask yourself some questions.
Is the white part of the eye pink already?
This pupil or cornea gray or white is the pupil round.
Can you see any foreign bodies?
Now you are ready to perform the reflex test.